<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: baseliner -->
  <Baseliner.label>obyčejník</Baseliner.label>
  <!-- EN: A naturally-evolved human with no major significant genetic modifications. -->
  <Baseliner.description>Základní vývojová větev člověka bez jakýchkoli významných genetických modifikací.</Baseliner.description>
  
  <!-- EN: dirtmole -->
  <Dirtmole.label>krtkoun</Dirtmole.label>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, they thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are extremely capable at digging or mining tasks. In the open, however, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance.\n\nAfter the first tunnel colonies failed due to the stress of confinement, colonization agencies began genetically altering colonists to live without open space or sunlight. This xenotype is known colloquially as the dirtmoles. Today, dirtmoles have expanded out of their original tunnel homes and rule many confined spaces in the anthrosphere. They can be found in deep mines, cramped low-tech spacecraft, and teeming by the billions in the dark underlayers of countless urbworlds. -->
  <Dirtmole.description>Se šedou kůží adaptovanou na umělé světlo se krtkouni vyžívají ve stísněných a tmavých prostorech, kde se souboje a cestování odehrávají na relativně krátkých vzdálenostech. Jsou velmi schopní v kopání a těžení. Za to ale trpí, pokud jsou vystaveni slunečnímu světlu, které je spaluje. Také na větších otevřených prostranstvích jim nepomáhá jejich pomalá rychlost ani krátkozrakost.\n\nPoté, co selhaly první podzemní kolonie na stres a ponorkovou nemoc, kolonizační agentury začaly vývoj na upraveném lidském genomu, jehož nositelé jsou schopni žít ve stísněných prostorech bez slunečního světla. Členům tohoto xenotypu se hovorově říká krtkouni. Už je to dlouho, co krtkouni opustili jejich původní podzemní doupata a začali vládnout mnoha dalším uzavřeným prostorům na světě. Často se nachází v hlubokých dolech, stísněných primitivních vesmírných lodích či po miliardách v hlubinách nezpočetných městských světů.</Dirtmole.description>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, dirtmoles thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are naturals at digging and navigating complex tunnel structures. In the open, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance. -->
  <Dirtmole.descriptionShort>Se šedou kůží adaptovanou na umělé světlo se krtkouni vyžívají ve stísněných a tmavých prostorech, kde se souboje a cestování odehrávají na relativně krátkých vzdálenostech. Jsou přirozenými mistry v hloubení a zdolávání složitých tunelových komplexů. Naopak venku trpí při vystavení slunečnímu světlu, pomalou rychlostí a krátkozrakostí.</Dirtmole.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: genie -->
  <Genie.label>džin</Genie.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies' delicate bones and natural aptitude with machines allow them to manipulate devices with remarkable precision. They are emotionally cold and can follow orders where others might panic. However, they are fragile, and their amplified nerve impulses make them easy to debilitate with relatively little pain. With so much of their brains dedicated to analyzing machines, they lack the neural hardware to analyze emotions, so they sometimes come off as socially inept. Their dead calm makes it even harder for them to relate to what they see as madly-hotheaded baseliner humans.\n\nGenies were engineered thousands of years ago by a long-disbanded space navy to hold engineering positions on large starships. Today, genies still serve as engineers in great cities and fleets, but many can also be found working as lawyers, pilots, and musicians. -->
  <Genie.description>Vytvořeni pro to být inženýry, džinové mají sice křehké kosti, ale zato jsou velmi schopní se stroji, což jim s nimi umožňuje manipulovat s pozoruhodnou přesností. Jsou emocionálně chladní a nemají problém poslouchat rozkazy i v situacích, ve kterých by se ostatní zhroutili. Na druhou stranu jsou velmi zranitelní a i relativně malá bolest je schopná je zneschopnit. Vzhledem k tomu, jak velkou část mozku mají specializovanou na analyzování strojů, jim nezbyl prostor pro analyzování lidských emocí, což je příčinou jejich nemotornosti v jakékoli společenské interakci. To že jsou smrtelně klidní, jim také zabraňuje v tom se ztotožnit s pro ně až příliš horkohlavými obyčejníky.\n\nDžinové byli vytvořeni tisíce let zpět dávno rozpadlým vesmírným námořnictvem, aby zastávali inženýrské pozice na obřích hvězdných lodích. Dnes jsou džinové stále převážně inženýři ve velkoměsteh a vesmírných flotilách, ale značná část z nich pracuje i jako právníci, piloti či muzikanti.</Genie.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies have natural aptitude with machines, and are emotionally cold and calm. They are also fragile and vulnerable to pain. Focused on machines, they often come off as socially inept. -->
  <Genie.descriptionShort>Vytvořeni pro to být inženýry, jsou velmi schopní se stroji, přičemž jsou také emocionálně chladní a klidní. Jsou také velmi křehcí a náchylní na bolest. Jsou tak moc zaměření na stroje, že jsou velmi nešikovní v jakékoli sociální interakci.</Genie.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: highmate -->
  <Highmate.label>TODO</Highmate.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence.\n\nOn a few wealthy worlds, highmate xenogerms are commercially available and some people become highmates as a sort of career. However, many societies find them abhorrent, either because they distract people from forming natural families, or because they are humans shaped to serve the pleasures of another. On such worlds they are either reserved as playthings of the powerful, or banned entirely. This particular line of highmate fits the fashions of classical Novaroma, but many other variants exist. -->
  <Highmate.description>TODO</Highmate.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence. -->
  <Highmate.descriptionShort>TODO</Highmate.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: hussar -->
  <Hussar.label>husar</Hussar.label>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice, which also makes them less likely to rebel against their commanders.\n\nWhile hussars' emotions make them dangerous in combat, they can't relate to baseliner humans. They are famous for their blood-red eyes and "hussar stare", a dead expression that unsettles many people. Their lack of expression and burning aggressive nature has led to many violent misunderstandings.\n\nIn most societies where they live, hussars are kept separated from the rest of the population. Hussars are single-purpose tools - and they generally aren't bothered by the fact. -->
  <Hussar.description>Husaři jsou supervojáci vyvinuti genetickou úpravou, přičemž jsou velmi zdatní v boji a s přesnou muškou, rychle se jim hojí zraňení, vydrží extrémní teploty a bez problémů užívají schopnosti vylepšující drogy. Mají genetickou závislost na šťávě-go, což je dělá oddanějšími vůči jejich vůdcům.\n\nZatím co jejich emoce je dělají velmi nebezpečnými v boji, nerozumí si s obyčejníky. Jsou proslulí svýma krvavě rudýma očima a jejich "husarským pohledem", výrazem, který znepokojuje ostatní kolem. Jejich slabé schopnosti vyjadřování společně s jejich velmi agresivní povahou mají na svědomí mnoho krvavých nedorozumění.\n\nVe většině společností, ve kterých žijí, jsou odděleni od zbytku populace. Husaři jsou jednoúčelové nástroje, ale netváří se, že by jim to nějak vadilo.</Hussar.description>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice. -->
  <Hussar.descriptionShort>Husaři jsou supervojáci vyvinuti genetickou úpravou, přičemž jsou velmi zdatní v boji a s přesnou muškou, rychle se jim hojí zraňení, vydrží extrémní teploty a bez problémů užívají schopnosti vylepšující drogy. Mají genetickou závislost na šťávě-go.</Hussar.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: impid -->
  <Impid.label>čerťák</Impid.label>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impid cultures live on many rimworlds and dry deathworlds. Impids are extremely fast-moving, easily tolerate high temperatures, and can spew fire from their mouths. Though they are masters on the sand, impids struggle in other environments. They are terrible with farming. They fight well at range, but in close combat their physical weakness becomes apparent.\n\nOutlanders call them dustrunners because of their speed over open terrain and resistance to heat. Some tribes call them devils because of their horns and because they burn their enemies. Impid tribes' combat tactics usually center on rapid-approach incendiary attacks using both handheld fire weapons and their fire spew ability. -->
  <Impid.description>Vyvinuti pro život v poušti, čerťácké kultury žijí na mnoha okrajových a mrtvých světech. Čerťáci jsou velmi rychlí, odolní vůči vysokým teplotám a jsou schopni chrlit oheň. I přesto že, jsou páni pouště, mají problém přežít v jakémkoli jiném podnebí, nejsou schopni farmařit a mají slabý imunitní systém. Jsou to zdatní střelci, zato boj zblízka je pro ně znatelnou slabinou.\n\nOdpadlíci jim říkají prachoběžci pro jejich rychlost na volném terénu a odolnost vůčí teplu. Některé kmeny je nazývají ďábly pro jejich rohy a oblibu upalovat svoje nepřátele. Bojové strategie kmenů čerťáků jsou běžně zaměřené jak na rychlý příchod, tak na použití zápalných zbraní, ať už mechanických nebo biologických.</Impid.description>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impids are very fast, can spew fire from their mouths, and easily tolerate high temperatures. They fight well at range, but in close combat they do little damage. They are terrible with farming, and have weak immune systems. -->
  <Impid.descriptionShort>Vyvinuti pro život v poušti, čerťáci jsou velmi mrštní, jsou schopni chrlit oheň a nemají problém odolávat vysokým teplotám. Jsou zdatní střelci, zatímco nejsou moc zběhlí v boji zblízka ani ve farmaření a mají slabý imunitní systém.</Impid.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: neanderthal -->
  <Neanderthal.label>neandertálec</Neanderthal.label>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. Their most salient characteristic is that they are difficult to hurt: They are very resistant to injury, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, without ever having evolved in a complex civilization, they are less adept than baseliner humans at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis was originally an archaic population of hominids that emerged over 200,000 years ago during the Pleistocene epoch. After they were replaced by and merged with humans 30,000 years ago, they were absent for tens of thousands of years until scientists resurrected them from ancient DNA. Neanderthals now survive in sub-societies on some settled planets. On the rimworlds, neanderthal tribes carve out the same existence as their Earth ancestors did so long ago. -->
  <Neanderthal.description>Neandertálci jsou podsadití, velmi silní humanoidi. Jejich hlavní charakteristikou je jejich odolnost vůči jakýmkoli zraněním, protože mají slabší vnímání bolesti a silný imunitní systém. Jejich slabými stránkami jsou naopak intelektuální a sociální činnosti, které jsou užitečné pro komplexnější civilizace. Jejich impulsivní chování může být nebezpečné až agresivní.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis byla původní populace hominidů, která se původně vyvinula kolem 200 000 let před naším letopočtem v epoše pleistocénu. Poté, co byli nahrazeni aktuální větví lidí, vyhynuli před zhruba 30 000 lety našeho letopočtu. Však v nedávné době se vědcům povedlo oživit členy této vývojové linie z jejich dochovaných pozůstatků DNA. Neandertálci se v dnešní době nachází na některých osídlených planetách v uzavřených komunitách. Na některých okrajových světech žijí kmeny neandertálců stejným způsobem, jakým žili i jejich předci před vyhynutím na zemi.</Neanderthal.description>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. They are hardy and difficult to injure, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, their minds are less adept at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive. -->
  <Neanderthal.descriptionShort>Neandertálci jsou podsadití, velmi silní humanoidi. Jsou velmi odolní vůči zraněním i infekcím, zato jejich mysl nezvládá sociální a intelektuální úkony a také se chovají velmi bez rozmyslu a nebezpečně impulsivně.</Neanderthal.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: pigskin -->
  <Pigskin.label>prasokožec</Pigskin.label>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids which are capable of two-legged movement, tool use, and speech, but which also retain many pig-like qualities. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands leave them at a disadvantage when attempting to precisely manipulate tools and objects. They don't see well at a distance, so pigskin gangs usually focus on close-range weapons. They also have a strong taste for explosives.\n\nPigskins were made for their organs. Uncomfortable with the idea of harvesting organs from baseliner humans, a long-gone government merged human DNA into pigs to make the animals produce more easily-transplantable hearts and lungs. They succeeded, but the resulting creatures became more humanlike than anyone anticipated. -->
  <Pigskin.description>Prasokožci jsou hybridi mezi člověkem a prasetem, kteří jsou schopni vzpřímeného pohybu, používání nástrojů a mluvi, přičemž stále mají některé rysy prasat. Jsou vytrvalí a mají žaludek, který je schopen strávit všechno, co spolykají, ale jejich prasečí ruce jsou pro ně velkou nevýhodou při jakékoli práci s nástroji. Jsou krátkozrací, takže se primárně soustředí na zbraně pro boj zblízka. Také rádi používají všelijaké výbušniny.\n\nPrasokožci byli vytvořeni pro pěstování orgánů, které narozdíl od těch čistě prasečích jsou daleko lépe transplantovatelné do lidského těla. Nepříjemná představa sklízení orgánů obyčejníků dovedla jednu z již neexistujících vlád ke sloučení DNA prasat a lidí a tím vytvořit nelidské dárce orgánů. V jejich misi uspěli, ale vzniklí tvorové byli mnohem lidštější, než se očekávalo.</Pigskin.description>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands are bad at fine manipulation. They don't see well at a distance, so they usually focus on close-range weapons. They have a strong taste for explosives. -->
  <Pigskin.descriptionShort>Prasokožci jsou hybridi mezi člověkem a prasetem. Jsou vytrvalí a mají žaludek, který je schopen strávit všechno, co spolykají, ale jejich ruce jsou příliš nemotorné pro jemnou manipulaci. Jsou také krátkozrací, takže preferují zbraně na blízko a také rádi používají výbušniny.</Pigskin.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: sanguophage -->
  <Sanguophage.label>sanguofág</Sanguophage.label>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are a type of archotech-enhanced xenohuman. Powered by archites, their abilities go far beyond normal genetic enhancements. They are mentally adept and preternaturally beautiful. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. They don't age or die naturally and never suffer from disease or poison. A sanguophage can make a new sanguophage by reimplanting their own xenogerm into a person.\n\nSanguophages must regularly consume hemogen derived from human blood, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light.\n\nThe first sanguophage appeared thousands of years ago when the lord-explorer Varan-Dur sought to control a hyperintelligent archotech and found himself transformed by it instead. Every sanguophage is descended from him. Since then, sanguophages have often been hunted because of their destabilizing power and their need for blood. Since they can pass for baseliners, many live in hiding among typical humans.\n\nTheir numbers are unknown. Some think they are legends or rare irrelevancies. Some believe sanguophages secretly direct entire human civilizations. The stories speak of eternal lords ruling billions from slate-black space stations, or directing blood sacrifices at conferences in the underlayers of the deepest urbworlds. -->
  <Sanguophage.description>Sanguofágové jsou archotecky upravený xenotyp lidí. Poháněni archity, jejich schopnosti sahají až za hranice obyčejného genetického inženýrství. Jsou mentálně na výši, nadpřirozeně krásní a v boji jsou schopni vystřelit smrtící ostny a vyléčit spojence. Nestárnou, ani přirozeně neumírají a nikdy nepodlehnou nemoci či otravě. Sanguofágové jsou schopni vytvořit další sanguofágy použitím jejich vlastní genovštipovací metody.\n\nSanguofágové musí pravidelně konzumovat hemogen z lidské krve a také musí pravidelně mrtvospát. Jsou náchylní na spálení ohněm a omezeni slunečním zářením.\n\nPrvní sanguofágové se poprvé zjevili několik tisíc let zpět, když lord Varan-Dur se chtěl pokusit ovládnout hyperinteligentní archotechnologii, ale namísto toho byl transformován v prvního novodobého sanguofága. Všichni sanguofágové jsou jeho potomci. Od té doby byli sanguofágové loveni pro jejich přílišnou moc a pro jejich potřebu konzumovat lidskou krev. Tím, že vzhledově jsou velmi podobní obyčejníkům, tak často žijí v ústraní mezi obyčejnými lidmi.\n\nJejich počty jsou neznámé, a proto si někteří myslí, že jsou pouze legendami. Jiní zase věří v to, že sanguofágové ovládají chod celé lidské civilizace. Tradují se příběhy o lordech ovládající miliardy ze své břidlicové vesmírné stanice či o ukrývajících sanguofázích, plánujících krvavé oběti ze skrytých konferencí z nejhlubšího podsvětí městských světů.</Sanguophage.description>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are ageless, deathless super-humans powered by archotech-created archites in the bloodstream. They are beautiful and extremely intelligent. They can heal any injury, and never suffer from disease or poison. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. The price is that sanguophages must consume hemogen derived from human blood to survive, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light. -->
  <Sanguophage.descriptionShort>Sanguofágové jsou nestárnoucí, nesmrtelní superlidé pohánění archity v jejich krevnim toku. Jsou nadpřirozeně krásní a inteligentní. Také jsou schopni speciálně ošetřit zranění a netrpí nemocemi, ani otravou jedy. V boji mohou používat kostnaté ostny jako projektily. Cena těchto všech schopností je, že musí konzumovat hemogen pocházející z lidské krve a musí pravidelně a dlouze mrtvospát. Jejich další slabinou je oheň a sluneční světlo.</Sanguophage.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: waster -->
  <Waster.label>pustinář</Waster.label>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo.\n\nOriginally engineered to prevent resettlement of post-apocalyptic deathworlds, wasters are living area-denial weapons. Waster pirates armed with toxic weapons are the bane of many frontier peoples, both on the rimworlds and in the depths of the urbworld hyperstructures. -->
  <Waster.description>Jsou agresivní, toxinům imunní, nemocem odolní a mohou užívat psychit a budíček bez negativních účinků. Vedlejší efekt jejich metabolismu je potřeba konzumovat psychit, který má většinou formu vločky nebo jája.\n\nPůvodně stvořeni pro znemožnění znovuosídlení postapokalyptických mrtvých světů, pustináři jsou živoucí území okupující zbraně. Pustinářští piráti ozbrojeni toxickými zbraněmi jsou častou překážkou pohraničních národů žijících jak na okrajových světech, tak v hyperstrukturách městských světů.</Waster.description>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo. -->
  <Waster.descriptionShort>Jsou agresivní, toxinům imunní, nemocem odolní a mohou konzumovat psychit a budíček bez negativních efektů. Vedlejší efekt jejich metabolismu je potřeba konzumovat psychit, který má většinou formu vločky nebo jája.</Waster.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: yttakin -->
  <Yttakin.label>yttakín</Yttakin.label>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments. Yttakin share a psychic connection with the wildlife and can summon animals to their side during battles. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before.\n\nSince they migrated off their icy birthworld of Yttak, Yttakin settlements live on many planets. Their fur, roaring voices, and aversion to urban living sometimes leads naive outsiders to believe they are simple-minded animals. Quick-minded Yttakin are happy to make good use of such wrong beliefs, whether at the negotiating table or on the battlefield. -->
  <Yttakin.description>Yttakíni jsou potomci kolonistů vytvořených pro osídlení extrachladných planet. Jejich značná velikost a hrubá srst jim značně zjednodušuje pobyt v promrzlých prostředích. Yttakíni také sdílejí psychické spojení s okolní přírodou a jsou schopni povolat okolní zvířata do boje. Nejsou sice rychlí ani zruční, ale za to jsou schopni vytrvat, zatímco jiní by už dávno zkolabovali.\n\nOd chvíle kdy první yttakíni opustili svoji domovskou planetu Yttak, se usídlili na mnoha planetách. Jejich srst, řvavý hlas a odmítání městského způsobu života často vede naivní odpadlíky k přesvědčení že jsou to pouze slabomyslná zvířata. Yttakíni rádi využívají těchto falešných přesvědčení a to ať při důležitých jednáních anebo na bojišti.</Yttakin.description>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments, and they have a unique ability to communicate vocally and psychically with animals. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before. -->
  <Yttakin.descriptionShort>Yttakíni jsou potomci kolonistů vytvořených pro osídlení extrachladných planet. Jejich značná velikost a hrubá srst jim značně zjednodušuje pobyt v promrzlých prostředích a jednou z jejich schopností je komunikovat se zvířaty. Nejsou sice rychlí, ani zruční, ale za to jsou schopni vytrvat, zatímco jiní by už dávno zkolabovali.</Yttakin.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>